<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <description></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 12:40:55 -0400</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>Neighborhood Average Age through Citibike Usage</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/05/02/bike-share-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/05/02/bike-share-2.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Citibike makes data available for all rides on their network. We have the starting station location of each trip, and for most trips, the birth year of the rider. I approximated age from the birth year variable, and using the Google API, I associated each Citibike station with a neighborhood in NYC (e.g., Chelsea or Williamsburg). I then looked at the average age of riders by starting neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/citibike_age_neigh.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; title=&quot;Age Neighborhood&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common age (mode) is actually the same for UWS and Williamsburg - 31 years old. The distrutions below show why the averages are so different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/age_distributions.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; title=&quot;Age Neighborhood&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used a combination of pandas, R (ggplot), and seaborn to produce these graphics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2016 10:15:31 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Citibike Heatmaps 2016</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/05/01/bike-share-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/05/01/bike-share-1.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a heatmap of Citibike usage across an entire year, with each day as a column and every 15 minutes as a row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/citibike_full_2016.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; title=&quot;Citibike Heatmap 2016&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We immediately see the distinction between working days, where people use the bikes to get to and from work, and weekends and holidays, where riding primarily occurs during the day. It is also clear that riding peaks in September and October which can be explained by the great fall weather. To focus on commuting behavoir, I removed all weekends and holidays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/citibike_working_2016.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; title=&quot;Citibike Heatmap 2016&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at rides on weekdays, we see that commutes home truly start at 5pm, there is a clear distinction moving from the 4:45 - 5:00 increment to the 5:00 - 5:15 increment. Similarly, there is a drop off from the 8:45 - 9:00 increment to the 9:00 - 9:15 increment. There is also a relatively dark area between 10:45 and 11:30 which I believe captures the lull between commutes to work and the lunch rush.
&lt;br /&gt;
I used pandas to combine the quarterly CSVs made available by Citibike, and then exported a group by function to R where I used ggplot to produce these heatmaps.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 10:15:31 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
